Okay, בוקר טוב Boker tov everybody. בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף
daf is קמ"ה Kuf Mem Hey 145. We had just ended yesterday
with reading the משנה Mishna on קמ"ד עמוד ב. Kuf Mem Daled
amud bet. And to remind you, this was the case of שושבינות,
shushbinut, which is the people that go, the close friends of the
groom, but it also refers to the gifts. And the basic story
was that in this family here, I don't know, let's say יעקב,
Yaakov, whatever, his friend שמעון's Shimon son was getting married. So he
sent as a representative of the family,
his son here, and to go ahead and to bring a gift
and to be one of the שושבינות shushbinot at the pre-wedding party.
Then he dies and then the same person who represented the family
is now getting married and they're sending a gift to him. And
the question is, how much is that gift specifically for the groom
and how much is it really paying back because there was very
much, as the משנה Mishna says, this is considered actually a legally
binding obligation that if you received one of this gift at your
wedding that you have to then pay it back or your family
received for your child's wedding.
I don't know exactly about how we sort of fix the exact
dollar value, but anyway that you have an obligation to pay it
back. So therefore, how much is this seen as being giving back
to the son and therefore he keeps it, or giving back to
the family and it's divided? So the משנה Mishna said that it
is given back to the family and the son was only representing
the family. Okay and it contrasted that to if it was just
the son was just bringing a normal gift, and it says that
is not something that can be collected in בית דין Beis Din
even though there will normally be reciprocity and the implication being that
if then a gift is given back after the father is dead
but it's given to the son, that is specifically to the son.
But because of the specific like legal structure of this, this is
understood to be a legal obligation to the family, not to the
son, and therefore being given back to the family. So why is
the wedding context...
that was the nature of שושבינות. shushbinut. That was the nature in
which there was this legal obligation of reciprocity, you know?
So because of that, since this was coming from the family, the
son was seen only as a representative. Isn't that sort of a
way that the community in effect shares the cost of the wedding?
Yes, although this was prior to the wedding, not actually... well, we'll
see. No, I take that back. I take that back. It's actually,
I think
you're right. It actually is during the time of the wedding itself,
but it's not so clear that it's the cost of like paying
for the wedding for all of the guests. It seems like it's
more like, you know, the specific gifts given to the family. I
mean, so I don't know. I mean, maybe that has something to
do with it, you know, because I laid out 50,000 dollars for
my son's wedding, but I know I can expect a certain amount
of gifts from the שושבינות. shushbinot. I'm not sure that it was
exactly about that, but who knows? It might have been. It might
have been. Yeah, this obligation of reciprocity, if I invite a family
for a שבת... Shabbos... Right, exactly, exactly. And here the... right, it
wasn't that they were coming with like, you know, with all of
the catered food at the wedding, right? So we'll see, actually, it
seems like it might even... well, we'll see, we'll see as we
get through the גמרא. Gemara. Like a baby shower concept? Oh, that's
a nice way of thinking about it, right. Everybody brings it when
it's the next turn to... right, the cycle of friends that goes
around and every time somebody has the baby they all sort of
give the gift at the 17th cycle, the stuff finally gets worn
out. Okay, רמי, Rami, I'll ask you, says the גמרא. Gemara. Everybody's
always regifting the exact same gift. It's basically like, don't even bother
opening the packaging, we'll just put a new card on it.
Okay, eventually somebody finally opens it and it's an empty box. Okay,
anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says, רמי, Rami, I'll ask you on
this: שלח לו אביו שושבינות. Shalach lo aviv shushbinot. The father sent
the שושבינות shushbinot to this guy while the father was alive. כשהיא
חוזרת חוזרת לו. Keshechozeret chozeret lo. When it gets paid back, if
the father's dead and it's given to this son's wedding, it's seen
as a specific gift to him and not to the whole family.
So how do you reconcile this? So the גמרא Gemara says: כשהיא
חוזרת לו. Keshechozeret lo. נשתלחה לאביו, Nishtalcha le'aviv, נשתלחה לאביו שושבינות, כשהיא
חוזרת חוזרת מן האמצע. nishtalcha l'aviv shoshbinut keshe'hi chozeret chozeret min ha'emtza.
However, before we get to the reconciliation, however, let's say the father
while he was still alive, he was first and a gift was
sent to his son. And then the father dies. So now and
now it's their turn to reciprocate. So when they're reciprocating, the gift
to the son was seen as a gift to the family. So
their obligation to reciprocate is not his personal obligation, it's an obligation
of the estate, right? Because it was a gift to the family,
and therefore the whole family... the money for the reciprocation for the
gift going back has to come from the whole family. So it's
a little... so it's lax parallel, right? The gift to is a
gift to the whole family, and therefore the money for the gift
back comes from the whole family. Whereas here the gift to, you
know, might have been a gift to the family, but when it's
given, it's... seen as being given to that specific son. Now that
again, that does not, that's not like that that that lack of
parallel is possible, right? You understand? It's coming from the family to
an individual person. Okay, so when they sent it, they sent it
to that individual person. When it comes back, you know, so that's
sort of, so I'm sorry, so if this came first, it was
gifted here, okay, it came from the family to the individual son,
then the father dies, and then the family gives it back to
the individual son. So that's that the gift comes from the family
to the groom. All right, so that's like a like a lack
of symmetry. From the entire family to the specific groom. So that's
the way the ברייתא Braita assumes it, and therefore the ברייתא Braita
says that therefore, if this son represented the family and gave it
to the groom, then the father dies, then it comes back, it
comes back to the groom. You got that? From the family to
the groom. That's the concept, not from family to family, and not
from groom to groom, from family to the groom. All right, so
that's against our משנה Mishna though. That says that the groom keeps
it himself. So אמר רבי אסי אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Assi
Amar Rabbi Yochanan כי תנינא נמי מתניתין נשתלחה לאביו תנינא. ki tnan
nami matnitin nishtalcha l'aviv tnan. So the גמרא Gemara tries to rewrite
the משנה. Mishna. The גמרא Gemara says let's adopt the ברייתא Braita
as the basic rule, and according to the ברייתא Braita basically the
rule would be that it comes from the family to the groom.
So when the משנה Mishna says that it goes back to the
entire family, so it says don't read it that way. We have
to switch the גרסא girsa in the משנה. Mishna. The language in
the משנה Mishna is חזרה לאמצע. chazra l'emtza.
So it says don't read the משנה Mishna that, here let's read
the משנה Mishna again. The
משנה Mishna is האחים שעשו מקצתן שושבינות. ha'achim she'asu miktzatan shoshbinut.
So he says don't read it as that they went ahead and
gave a gift to the son, don't read it that way. הכי
קתני, hachi katani, כי תנינא נמי מתניתין נשתלחה לאביו תנינא. ki tnan
nami matnitin nishtalcha l'aviv tnan. It means that it's not that they
were the שושבינות shoshbinot בחיי אביהם. bechayei avihem. No, no, no. Read
the משנה Mishna like the ברייתא, Braita, the opposite order. They were
the recipients, okay? And because they were the recipients, therefore it's coming
back from the entire family. So our read of the משנה Mishna
is they were the gifter and it goes back to the entire
family, which is a parallel but it's not the ברייתא. Braita. The
ברייתא Braita is it goes to the son, to the individual. So
he says don't read that our משנה. Mishna. Read our משנה Mishna
the reverse. They were the recipients, or the son was the recipient,
and it goes back from the entire family. Where is it in
the ברייתא Braita that it's coming from the entire family? נשתלחה לאביו
שושבינות nishtalcha le'aviv shushbinot, כשהיא חוזרת חוזרת מן האמצע. keshechozeret chozeret min
ha'emtza.
If they were the recipients, then when they give it back, it
goes back from the entire family. Okay, fine. Okay, so כי תנינא
נמי מתניתין נשתלחה לאביו תנינא. ki tnan nami matnitin nishtalcha l'aviv tnan.
Fine, have our משנה Mishna match the ברייתא, Braita, rewrite it. The
only point is that the text is completely against us. Are we
understanding it or actually rewriting it? We're rewriting it. והאחים שעשו מקצתן
שושבינות קתני. v'ha'achim she'asu miktzatan shoshbinut katani. What do you mean? Our
משנה Mishna says, sounds like no, it started that they gave the
gift, not that it started with them receiving the gift. No, no,
הכי קתני, hachi katani, so תני למקצתן. tni l'miktzatan. No,
it doesn't mean that they were שושבינות shoshbinot for some of, excuse
me, some of them were שושבינות shoshbinot for this other family, but
they received שושבינות, shoshbinot, some of them were the recipients of, we're
completely rewriting the ברייתא. Braita. וחזרה שושבינות מקצתן? v'chazra shoshbinut miktzatan?
But one minute, but then it says that when they receive it
back it goes to the groom. So the גמרא Gemara says no,
הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, חזרה לגבות לגבות מן האמצע. chazra ligvot ligvot
min ha'emtza. No, no, no, when it's their time now to pay
up, not when it's now they're receiving it. They pay from the
middle. Okay, so obviously that's a very impossible rewrite of the whole
משנה. Mishna. All right, so we, I mean, it's impossible if you're
going to keep the same text, it's impossible to understand. Yes, if
you've got enough eraser and enough ink, you can rewrite it. Fine,
but it's not what the משנה Mishna is saying. רב אשי אמר
Rav Ashi amar anyway, fine. So our משנה Mishna seems to be,
seems to not be the ברייתא. Braita. So we're going to have
better answers. רב אשי אמר לא קשיא כאן בסתם כאן במפרש. lo
kashya kan bistam kan bimfaresh. It depends, it depends what the context
is, which is a much easier answer. Okay? Is the context that
the son is representing the family? Then it goes back to the
whole family. Is the context seen as the son is representing himself
or seen as specifically focused on the son? Then it goes back
to the son. How do you have that though? How? Right, well,
right, exactly. כדתניא. kidtanya. שלח לו אביו שושבינות כשהיא חוזרת חוזרת לו.
shelach lo aviv shoshbinut keshe'hi chozeret chozeret lo.
So the father sent a son as the שושבינות. shoshbinut. When it
comes back, it comes back to the specific son. Okay, so that's
like the ברייתא. Braita. The ברייתא Braita says that it goes back
to the specific groom. Now, so what's the case of the משנה
Mishna that it goes back to everybody? שלח אביו שושבינות shoshbinos? סתם
*shalach aviv shoshvinut stam*, if the father sent it סתם *stam*, okay,
then כשהיא חוזרת חוזרת לאמצע *keshehi chozeret chozeret le'emtza*, then it goes
back to the middle. So now the question is what's the difference
as sending it, you know, with an emphasis on the son, and
then it goes back to the son, that would be the ברייתא
braisa? *braita*, as opposed to sending it with the סתם *stam* as
more a anonymous representative of the family? So if you look at
the רשב"ם Rashbam, *Rashbam*, look at the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam*, okay, three
lines down in the wide lines, כדתניא *kitanya*, שלח לו אביו שושבינות
Shushbinot *shelach lo aviv shoshvinut*, כלומר נתן לו אביו מעות ושלחו לעשות
שושבינות Shushbinot כשהיא חוזרת חוזרת לו לבדו *klomar natan lo aviv ma'ot
v'shalcho la'asot shoshvinut keshehi chozeret chozeret lo levado*. Okay.
So what's the contrast to? אבל שלח אביו שושבינות shoshvinos סתם ולא
ייחד לאחד מבניו אף על פי שעל ידי אחד מבניו שלח אינו
חוזרת *aval shelach aviv shoshvinut stam v'lo yichad l'echad mi'banav af al
pi she'al yedei echad mi'banav shelach eino chozeret*. So what the רשב"ם
rashbam *Rashbam* says is it basically says ראובן *Reuven*, you go and
be the שושבינות shoshvinos *shoshvinut* for יעקב *Yaakov*’s son over there. Okay.
So if the father designates the particular son, then it's seen as
focusing on him and, you know, and he, it's about some personal
connection he has, and then when it comes back, it comes back
to him. If the father says, would one of you please take
out, you know, stop playing on your computer games and go be
a שושבין *shoshvin* for the other family, so one kid says, fine,
I'll do it. Okay. In that type of a case where he’s
not designating a particular son, he just is generic and represents the
family. Okay. The language is so when the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* says
נתן לו אביו מעות ושלחו *natan lo aviv ma'ot v'shalcho*, he gives
a gift to the kid and the kid brings it, right, so
then when it's changed to the feminine, לעשות שושבינות כשהיא חוזרת *la'asot
shoshvinut keshehi chozeret*, that's the שושבינא *shoshvina*, the שושבינא *shoshvina*, right, the
gift, right, yeah, yeah. Okay. All right. So fine. So it depends
whether the son is seen as to some degree, yes, he's representing
the family, but some degree with a focus on himself, or to
some degree as just a generic representative of the family. It's similar
to the previous משנה *mishna* about when the kid gets a job,
is hired for a job, is he hired, you know, sort of
on his own merit or is he hired on his family's merit,
right? And so that affects whether the money that comes back is
coming back to him or coming back to the family. Yeah, I
would have thought that, you know, it would be sort of a
little bit different. Are you sending the gift to like the ראובן
*Reuven* family or are you sending it to the חתן chatan שמעון
*chatan Shimon*, you know what I mean? Like that has to determine.
Right, yeah, I would agree with it too. Like, you know, it’s
not, yeah, so I think there are other contexts that could determine.
You know, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* isn't clear, the רשב"ם Rashbam, *Rashbam*
gives his interpretation of that difference. Okay. ושמואל אמר *v'Shmuel amar*, שמואל
*Shmuel* says, הכא ביבם עסקינן *hacha b'yavam askinan*, we’re talking about a
brother-in-law. Okay. What does? So, now, so what does that mean? והכא
ביבם עסקינן *v'hacha b’yavam askinan* שאינו נוטל בראוי כבמוחזק *she'eino notel b'ra'uy
k'vemuchzak*,
and he does not get in stuff that was deserving to come
back as if it was already מוחזק muchzak. *muchzak*. So what does
that mean? If you look at the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* five lines
down, ושמואל אמר לעולם כדתני ברייתא braitah דאף השולח שושבינות על ידי
אחד מבניו חוזרת לאותו הבן לבדו *v'Shmuel amar le'olam k'detani braita d'af
hasholeiach shoshvinut al yedei echad mi'banav chozeret l'oto haben levado*. The ברייתא
braitah. *braita* still dictates fundamentally it goes back to the son. So
what's the context in which it goes back to the entire family?
So he says ומתניתין דקתני חוזרת לאמצע הני מילי שמת הבן שנשלחו
שושבינות על ידו ורוצה היה להחזיר לו *u'matnitin diktani chozeret le'emtza hani
mili she'met haben she'nishalchu shoshvinut al yodo v'ratza haya lehachazir lo*. Okay.
So the case is like this. The real rule is like the
ברייתא *braita* that it goes back to the individual son. But here's
the case. The case is not only did the father die, the
son died. Okay. And this one here has now made יבום Yibum,
*yibum* with the son's wife. Okay. So what? That he wasn't appointed
so it goes back to the family? What? He wasn't a... so
right, so now right, what's... so the point is why... now first
of all, the first thing you should be asking is that if
it's the son's wife, the wedding's already over. So how is he
doing... right, where's the gift coming? The wedding already took place. So
the answer is that he's doing יבום *yibum*, let's say, after the
קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin* before the נשואין nisu'in, *nissuin*. The שושבינות *shoshvinut* was
part of the נשואין *nissuin*. All right. So anyway, so the son
does יבום *yibum* and now it's sort of saying like, well, I
get part of the thing I get for doing יבום *yibum*, in
addition to רות המואביה *Ruta HaMoaviah*, I get, you know, I get
the נחלה *nachala* of the son is I get everything, all his
חלק *chelek* in the ירושה
*yerusha*. I get his חלק *chelek*. So his חלק *chelek* included the
gift that was coming back to him. That's part of his חלק
*chelek* in the estate. And the answer is no, because that's ראוי
ra'uy *ra'uy*, that's not money that's already in possession of the estate,
that's a debt that has yet to be paid back. And since
it's a debt that has yet to be paid back, that you
don't get your brother's חלק *chelek* in the estate, that gets shared
by everybody. So the חתן *chatan*
died
between
the קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin* and six months later before the נשואין *nissuin*?
Correct. But if they like sent it earlier, like before the wedding,
then he would get it if it came to him? Yeah,
I mean, I don't think that was the
practice, but yes. Okay. Okay. So let's take
a look. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, now, שאינו נוטל בראוי
כבמוחזק *she'eino notel b'ra'uy k'vemuchzak*, מכלל mikhlal, דאידך משלם de'idach meshaleim, *michlal
d'idach m'shaleim*, so the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says that means that one
minute, let me just get this right. Right.
Right,
so the גמרא Gemara says but okay, but what you're basically saying
is is that in this case where the son died, they're still
obligated to give a gift back, right? It's just that it doesn't
go back to the יבם, Yabam, it goes to the whole family.
Right, so the גמרא Gemara says why's he obligated to give a
gift back?
The guy, there's no wedding of this guy that he's participating in.
Do you understand? He married, he died, this guy came in, okay?
So where is so he says what gift am I obligated to
give? Like you know, you don't do this whole big wedding thing
on a case of יבום, you do it like on a first
marriage or whatever. And this guy so he says I'm not even
obligated to give the gift in that scenario. Okay, but if the
יבם Yabam doesn't get it, why should the givers have to give?
If the יבם Yabam not only if he doesn't get it, but
if he's not you don't have the circumstances where the gift is
obligated. You don't have that wedding. You don't have that wedding. So
he says, גמרא Gemara says, מכלל, says the גמרא, Gemara דאידך משלם,
the other one has to pay. There they should be sending a
gift except it goes to the whole family. But why is that?
לימא תנו לי שושביני ואשמח עמו. Leima tnu li shoshvini ve'esmakh immo.
Let this guy say: Yeah, I'll give you the gift as soon
as you give me my friend who's getting married and let me
be part of the wedding and then I'll give the gift. But
right now this guy is dead, you know, so okay whatever. He's
dead and so I don't have to give the gift. Okay. מי
לא תניא, Mi lo tanya, did we not see a ברייתא? מקום
שנהגו להחזיר קידושין
מחזירין. Makom shene'hagu lehakhazir kiddushin makhzirin. Okay, so let's say nowadays we
talk about like if there's a break off of the engagement, do
you have to return the gift? You have to return the engagement
ring? So it says right. So basically if the woman died during
the after between the קידושין kiddushin and the נישואין, nisuin, okay, in
a place where the practice is in those cases that the bride's
family gives back the כסף קידושין, kesef kiddushin, okay, for us you
think about like the wedding ring. Okay. So that is the actual
money given in the קידושין kiddushin, act, and she died before the
נישואין, nisuin, so if the practice is to give that back in
those cases, you give it back. מקום שנהגו שלא להחזיר אין
מחזירין. Makom shene'hagu shelo lehakhazir ein makhzirin. If that's not the practice
you don't. You know, I funny that there could be an established
practice for this. You would hope that would be pretty rare. But
anyway, but also there was like years between the קידושין kiddushin and
the נישואין, nisuin, so maybe it wasn't so rare. Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara. says, ואמר רב יוסף בר אבא אמר מר עוקבא אמר
שמואל לא שנו אלא שמתה היא. ve'amar Rav Yosef bar Abba amar
Mar Ukva amar Shmuel, lo shanu ela shemeisa hi. That's when she
died. Okay. אבל מת הוא, Aval meis hu, but if he died,
the bride's family has no obligation to give it back. Why? אין
מחזירין. Ein makhzirin. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? Why? יכולה היא שתאמר שכינסה
תנו לי בעלי ואשמח עמו. Yekhola hi shetomar shekinsei: Tnu li ba'ali
ve'esmakh immo. I'm not giving back my ring. I'm ready to get
married. Just give me my husband and we'll get married. So it's
like I'm not it's not my fault, so it's not I'm not
obligated to give the ring. הכא נמי נימא תנו לי שושביני ואשמח
עמו. hacha nami neima tnu li shoshvini ve'esmakh immo. Let him say:
I don't have to give the gift, I'll give the gift when
we're having the wedding. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב יוסף
הכא במאי עסקינן, amar Rav Yosef: Hakha bemai askinan, what are we
talking about?
כגון ששמח עמו שבעה ימי משתה ולא הספיק לפרעו עד שמת. Kegon
shesamach immo shiva yemei mishteh velo hispik lifro'o ad shemeis. And this
is the question I was getting to earlier, Glory, about the timing.
Okay. It says: No, no, no, he didn't die after the קידושין,
kiddushin. they had a whole week of partying, whole week of the
wedding, and he died after שבע ברכות. sheva brachot. And presumably after
the week of partying you can't say like presumably if he had
died anytime in the middle of the week you could say, Since
I didn't get to spend the week partying with him, I'm not
obligated in it. Only after you spent the week partying are is
this guy now obligated in the gift. So it sounds like the
gifts came after,
or that they actually only maybe became fully obligatory
after you spent the week. You know, and therefore, in that case,
he is obligated in the gift and he doesn't give it specifically
to the יבם, yabam, it goes to the whole family. Presumably in
giving the gift. Right, I mean it could be the gifts came
early. I think more sort of conventionally it would have come earlier
on in the process, but to be legally obligated if you didn't
get to spend the whole week at the wedding, you know, with
the שבע ברכות, sheva brachot, it's not legally obligated. Yes. If a
חתן dies between קידושין kiddushin. and נישואין, nisuin, is she obligated to
שבעה shiva for him? No,
no, no. No obligation. שארו הקרוב אליו. She'eiro hakarov eilav. No, it's
only after נישואין. nisuin. Yeah. It's a מפורש ברייתא meforash braisa about
that. Yeah. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. לימא תנו
לי בעלי ואשמח עמו. Leima tnu li ba'ali ve'esmakh immo. So the
גמרא Gemara says: לימא תנו לי בעלי ואשמח עמו תנאי היא. Leima
tnu li ba'ali ve'esmakh immo tnai hi. Let's say this question about,
you know, whether I can say the issue about about giving back
the ring. giving back the כסף קידושין, kesef kiddushin, you know they
didn't have a ring in the time of the גמרא. Gemara Giving
back the כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin if the husband dies, let's say
that's a debate of
תנאים. Tannaim. דתניא ותנא בברייתא המארס את האישה Detanya v'tana b'braitah Hame'ares
es ha'ishah a man does ארוסין erusin בתולה גובה מאתיים ואלמנה מנה,
besulah govah masa'im v'almanah maneh, fine. So the and the בתולה besulah
gets two hundred, the אלמנה almanah one hundred even if let's say
he dies, you know, immediately after the קידושין. kiddushin. Okay, so that's
an interesting question in general whether the base amount of the כתובה
kesuvah is obligatory after the
קידושין. kiddushin מקום שנהגו להחזיר מחזיר מקום שנהגו שלא להחזיר אין מחזירין.
Makom shenahagu lehachazir machazir makom shenahagu shelo lehachazir ein machazirin. And now
again, for the first line to be a חידוש, chiddush, the two
hundred or the one hundred, it sounds like we would be talking
about immediately after the ארוסין. erusin. Okay, and nevertheless it says that
whether or not you have to give back the כסף קידושין kesef
kiddushin is dependent on what the practice is. דברי רבי נתן, Divrei
Rabbi Noson, that's what רבי נתן Rabbi Noson says. רבי יהודה הנשיא
אומר באמת אמרו, Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi omer be'emes amru, in fact they
said מקום שנהגו להחזיר מחזיר מקום שנהגו שלא להחזיר אין מחזירין. makom
shenahagu lehachazir machazir makom shenahagu shelo lehachazir ein machazirin. So that seems
to be just echoing, yeah, you're right. Actually that is what they
said. רבי יהודה הנשיא היינו תנא קמא, Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi hainu Tanna
Kama, isn't that exactly what the תנא קמא Tanna Kama just said?
אלא לאו תנו לי בעלי ואשמחה עמו איכא בינייהו. Ella lav t'nu
li ba'ali v'esmachah imo ika beina'ihu. It must be that what's going
on is a debate about what happens if he dies not after
the נשואין, excuse me, excuse me, if he dies, excuse me, if
the question about not about whether if he dies or whether it's
if she dies. Okay, איכא בינייהו וחסורי מחסרא והכי קתני. ika beina'ihu
v'chasurei mechasra v'hachi katani. It must be missing some words and here's
how you read it. Okay, המארס את האישה, Hame'ares es ha'ishah, somebody
did
ארוסין. erusin. Okay, בתולה גובה מאתיים ואלמנה מנה. besulah govah masa'im v'almanah
maneh. במה דברים אמורים, Bameh devarim amurim, now when is that that
there would be a
payment? דהדר ביה איהו. Dehadar bei ihu. Now he can't retract, it's
already קידושין. kiddushin, Okay, but if he basically like is מגרש migaresh
her, okay then, אבל מתה aval mesah if she died, so now
if she dies by the way she's not collecting the what do
you call it the כתובה, kesuvah, right, the כתובה kesuvah is only
if she gets divorced or if he dies. So in order to
create the
case of whatever, well let's just say מתה mesah if she dies
מקום שנהגו להחזיר מחזיר מקום שנהגו שלא להחזיר אין מחזירין. makom shenahagu
lehachazir machazir makom shenahagu shelo lehachazir ein machazirin. So it depends, so
does he have to give back the כסף קידושין? kesef kiddushin? That
depends on the מנהג. minhag. To the bride's family though. The fa-
no, she died, so the family give back, he has to give
back the כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin right to the father? No. No.
No, the bride died, does he, the groom, have to give back
the כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin to the bride's family?
Okay, what do you not understand? Didn't he give her כסף קידושין
kesef kiddushin yet? Oh, I'm sorry, you're right, I got it reversed.
Thank you Michael, thank you, thank you, you're right, you're right, I
got it reversed. Okay, thank you. Does the bride's family have to
give back, thank you, thank you Michael, give back the כסף קידושין
kesef kiddushin to the groom? Thank you. ודוקא שמתה היא, V'davka shemesah
hi, that's only if she died. אבל מת הוא Aval mes hu
if he dies אין מחזירין. ein machazirin. Then the bride's family does
not give it back.
מאי טעמא Mai ta'ama why? יכולה היא שתאמר תנו לי בעלי ואשמחה
עמו Yecholah hi shetomar t'nu li ba'ali v'esmachah imo because then she
can say look, I'm ready to get married, you know, resurrect him
and we'll get married. So otherwise I don't have to give back
the ring. ואתא רבי יהודה הנשיא למימר v'asa Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi lemeimar
and רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi is coming and saying באמת
אמרו be'emes amru in fact they said בין מת הוא ובין מתה
היא bein mes hu uvein mesah hi regardless of whether he dies
or she dies, whether you have to give back the ring or
not is based on the custom. מקום שנהגו להחזיר מחזיר מקום שנהגו
שלא להחזיר אין מחזירין Makom shenahagu lehachazir machazir makom shenahagu shelo lehachazir
ein machazirin ולא מצי אמרה תנו לי בעלי ואשמחה עמו. v'lo masi
amrah t'nu li ba'ali v'esmachah imo. Okay, so since it sounds like
רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi and רבי נתן Rabbi Noson are
saying the exact same thing, the גמרא Gemara created this gap between
them. Because you understand part of the problem is that the ברייתא
starts by saying that there's ארוסין, erusin, he has to pay a
hundred or two hundred. The only scenario of paying a hundred and
two hundred by you know is if he's the one who dies,
right? Everybody get that? That if she's the one who dies you're
not paying out the כתובה. kesuvah. And then and then it immediately
proceeds to say and you know whether you give back or not
the ring is dependent on the custom. So that's not convenient for
the גמרא Gemara because the גמרא Gemara wants to say that the
case of him dying is the debated case. So what the גמרא
Gemara does is it inserts in the middle, right, a different scenario.
If he dies you pay out, you pay out the כתובה. kesuvah.
If she dies then you have to give back the ring if
that's the custom. Okay, and then רבי Rebbi says actually even if
he dies you have to give back the ring if that's the
custom. So רבי Rebbi is saying you cannot say תנו לי בעלי
ואשמחה עמו t'nu li ba'ali v'esmachah imo even if he dies the
family would have to give back the ring if that were the
custom. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, so isn't that
one way to read it? I mean it's one way to read
it once you you know rewrite the ברייתא. So the גמרא Gemara
says לא lo not necessarily. דכולי עלמא יכולה שתאמר תנו לי בעלי
ואשמחה עמו. Dechulei alma yecholah shetomar t'nu li ba'ali v'esmachah imo. Everybody
would agree that if he were to die that she could say
I don't have to give back the ring. ובמת הוא כולי עלמא
לא פליגי. Uv'mes hu chulei alma lo pligi. And if he's the
one who dies then everybody agrees that she does not have to
give back the ring. כי פליגי Ki pligi when do they debate?
שמתה היא. shemesah hi. That she died. Now of course that's strange
because it sounded like everybody, so how do you read that in?
שמתה היא. Shemaisa hi. והכא בקידושין לטיבויי ניתנו קמיפלגי. Vehacha b'kiddushin letivuyei
nisnu kamiplegi. The question is whether קידושין kiddushin, is given over לטיבויי.
letivuyei.
So if you look at the רשב"ם, Rashbam it's exactly across from
this. רשב"ם Rashbam says לטיבויי ניתנו, letivuyei nisnu, שאם תמות ולא יזכה
לישאה יאבדו ולא יחזרו לו. she'im tamus v'lo yizkeh lise'ah ye'avdu v'lo
yachzeru lo. Okay, like לטיבויי letivuyei is like for pleasure, right? Right.
Okay, but meaning that right. So it's meaning it's the opposite. Meaning
we were sort of assuming like this.
Okay, it's like pushing everything down a level, okay? It's like he
dies, okay, and she dies. So we were saying if she dies,
the way we wanted to structure it was if she dies then
it's give back ring, or if that's the practice, okay, if that's
the מנהג, minhag, some places it wouldn't. If he dies, then it's
תנו לי בעלי, tnu li ba'ali, תנו לי בעלי, tnu li ba'ali,
never, never, you never give back the ring. Give back. Okay, that's
what we were suggesting, right? That, right, that's, yes, everybody, yeah? Okay,
that's what we were suggesting.
The גמרא Gemara is saying no, we're going to push it all
down. If he dies, it says everybody says, what the גמרא Gemara
says? לא דכולי עלמא יכולה שתאמר תנו לי בעלי ואשמח בו. lo
dekuli alma yeichola shetomer tnu li ba'ali ve'esmach bo. Okay, so if
he dies then everybody says never give back. So
where
we were trying to say that this was debated, okay, we were
trying to say that this was a מחלוקת, machlokes, okay, so the
גמרא Gemara, says no, this is כולי עלמא, kuli alma, right, everybody
agrees that if he dies you never give back. Okay,
דכולי עלמא יכולה שתאמר dekuli alma yeichola shetomer תנו לי בעלי. tnu
li ba'ali. Right, which means you never give it back. Give me
my husband and then I'll... okay. דכולי עלמא dekuli alma וכי פליגי
בשמתה היא והכא בקידושין לטיבויי ניתנו. veki peligi b'shemaisa hi vehacha b'kiddushin
letivuyei nisnu.
So here, she died, and the question really would be whether you
say that when the money is given for the קידושין, kiddushin, it's
like, you know, it's gone. Right, you know, it's dumped, yeah, that's
it, it's flushed away. It's flushed away.
Okay, so here the מחלוקת machlokes is whether she has to give
it back. Now, the problem is that it sounded like whether, it
sounded like that was based on a מנהג, minhag, מקום שנהגו להחזיר
לא נהגו להחזיר. makom shenahagu lehachzir lo nahagu lehachzir. Okay,
what we've done is we've switched the מנהג minhag to be this
case. This case is based on the מנהג. minhag. Oh no, wait,
excuse me, this case everybody agrees you never give it back. So
let's see how it goes. Okay, so the גמרא gemara says like
this: והכא בקידושין לטיבויי ניתנו קמיפלגי. vehacha b'kiddushin letivuyei nisnu kamiplegi. רבי
נתן סבר, Rabbi Nassan savar, okay, קידושין לאו לטיבויי ניתנו. kiddushin lav
letivuyei nisnu.
It's not, you know, given to be done with. And therefore it
would have to be given back if she was the one who
died, or at least it might be based on the מנהג. minhag.
ורבי יהודה הנשיא סבר קידושין לטיבויי ניתנו. v'Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi savar kiddushin
letivuyei nisnu. No, you're never going to get it back. So the
גמרא Gemara says one minute, but רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi
sounded like it would go back if that was the מנהג. minhag.
והא מקום שנהגו להחזיר מחזירין קתני. veha makom shenahagu lehachzir machzirin kasani.
But רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi also says that if the
מנהג minhag is to go back, it goes back. So the גמרא
Gemara says no. הכי קאמר. hachi ka'amar. בסבלונות bisavlonos ודאי מקום שנהגו
להחזיר מחזירין. vadai makom shenahagu lehachzir machzirin.
When it comes not to the קידושין, kiddushin, when it comes to
the סבלונות, savlonos, which is a type of gift, okay, that is
given that the groom sends during the אירוסין eirusin process period, that
is dependent on on the מנהג. minhag. Okay, so the way the
גמרא, Gemara so here's what you have. Okay, you have the ring,
okay, I don't know, we'll make it a diamond ring. Okay, I
don't know. Does that look like a diamond ring? Okay, that's for
the question about קידושין, kiddushin. whether that's, okay, that, then you have
the סבלונות, savlonos, which are the gifts that are sent from the
groom to the bride or the bride's family. What's the difference between
סבלונות savlonos and שושבינות? I'm going to tell you in a minute,
which is why I'm doing this. Okay, the groom is sending it
to the bride's family, to the bride or the bride's family. Here's
the bride's father. Okay, and this is, so this is the קידושין,
kiddushin. this is during the period of אירוסין eirusin he's sending gifts,
and then you have the נישואין nisuin
and you've got the חופה chuppah here, okay, and here comes the
bride. Okay, I didn't mean that. Anyway, and here she is, okay,
and in that case, you've got these people out here, the friends.
These are the שושבינין shoshbinin and they are coming to the חופה
chuppah and they're bringing their presents. Okay, that's supposed to be a
present. All right, so you got it? When he gives the ring,
does that go back? Giving the gifts, let's say he gives the
gifts, he sent during the engagement period, he sent fruit baskets. And
then these שושבינין shoshvinin and they are coming to the חופה chuppah
and they're bringing their present. Okay, that's supposed to be a present.
All right, so you got it? When he gives the ring, does
that go back? Giving the gift, let's say he gives the gifts,
he sent during the engagement period, he sent fruit baskets and flowers
and he sent all this various stuff during the engage- not the
engagement, during the betrothal period, okay, and then one of them dies
or whatever, then do you get it back, okay, and then there's
the- they get married, and these are the שושבינין shoshvinin come and
bring the gifts, and that's going to be repaid when one of
the שושבינין shoshvinin gets married. So there's all this giving back, right,
the giving back to the שושבינין shoshvinin when they get married, but
this is the giving back between the bride and the groom. Okay,
so now what we're saying here is is that first we said
that when she dies then it's based on the מנהג. minhag. The
first version: when he dies, okay, we tried to say there was
a מחלוקת machlokes because maybe she would never have to give back
if he died because she could say תנו לי בעלי ואת מכחימו.
tnuli ba'ali ve'at machimo. And now we're saying no, there's no מחלוקת.
machlokes. If he dies, you never give back. Okay, so what's the-
and they're debating whether you give back the כסף קידושין. kessef kiddushin.
So Rabbi Nassan says that's based on the מנהג minhag and Rebbe
says you never give it back. But the problem is but Rebbe
says also giving back is based on the מנהג. minhag. So no,
giving back based on the מנהג minhag is the giving back of
the סבלונות. sablonos. But the ring- the ring is hers to keep.
The כסף קידושין kessef kiddushin is hers to keep. The question of
the debate of the מנהג minhag is when- is about the giving
back of the סבלונות. sablonos. Okay, so let's read that again.
So Gemara says like this- איבעית אימא דכולי עלמא רבי נתן סבר
קידושין לאו לטיבועין ניתנו. ibayis eima dekuli alma Rabbi Nassan savar kiddushin
lav letibu'in nitnu. The ring is not necessarily given to be done
with and therefore if, you know, he dies, it's a- it's a
difference of מנהגים minhagim if it goes back. If he dies she
could say תנו לי בעלי ואת מכחימו, tnuli ba'ali ve'at machimo, but
if she dies it's a difference of מנהגים. minhagim. ורבי יהודה הנשיא
סבר קידושין לטיבועין ניתנו. VeRabbi Yehuda HaNasi savar kiddushin letibu'in nitnu. No,
the same way if he dies the ring doesn't go back, if
she dies the ring doesn't go back. The money given for the
כסף קידושין kessef kiddushin never goes back. So Gemara says ובמקום שנהגו
להחזיר מחזירין תניא. u'vemakom shenahagu lehachzir machzirin tanya. Okay, but the- but
what do you mean, Rebbe himself said when- if it's the מנהג
minhag to give it back, you give it back. No, הכי קאמר:
hachi ka'amar: the סבלונות- sablonos when it comes to the ring, that's
never going back. When it comes to the סבלונות sablonos ובמקום שנהגו
להחזיר מחזירין. u'vemakom shenahagu lehachzir machzirin. Okay, so that's what- that's Rebbe
said, that I will concede is based on the מנהג. minhag. והני
תנאי כהני תנאי. V'hani tannai kehani tannai. These תנאים, tannaim, Rabbi Nassan
and Rebbe, are like the following תנאים. tannaim. דתניא- D'tanya tana בריתא:
braisa: קידשה בכיכר- kidsha bekikar so he married her with a loaf
of bread.
בתולה גובה מאתיים ואלמנה מנה דברי רבי מאיר. besula gova masayim v'almana
maneh divrei Rabbi Meir. And then he died- fine. So you pay
the כסף kessef of the כתובה. kesuva. רבי יהודה אומר- Rabbi Yehuda
omer Rabbi Yehuda says: בתולה גובה מאתיים ואלמנה מנה ומחזרת לו את
השאר. besula gova masayim v'almana maneh u'machzeres lo es hashar. Fine, she
collects her כתובה, kesuva, but she returns the remainder. What's the remainder?
The- the bread. The bread goes back. Okay, so רבי יוסי אומר-
Rabbi Yosi omer קידשה בעשרים נותנים לה שלושים, חציה.
קידשה בשלושים
נותנים לה עשרים, חציה. kidsha be'esrim nosnim lah shloshim, chatzeiah. kidsha beshloshim
nosnim lah esrim, chatzeiah.
So he says, so we'll see this later- the Gemara's going to
sort of try to unpack this one, okay? If he married her
with thirty, give back twenty half; married her with twenty, give back
thirty half. The Gemara will get to that. So the Gemara says
like this: במאי עסקינן- bemai askinan what are you talking about? אילימא
שמתה- eilima shemesah she died. מי איכא כתובה- mi ika kesuva there's
no כתובה kesuva if she died. That's what I was telling you
earlier, right? The standard scenario of all these payments is that he's
dying. So I'm gonna start to sort of, you know, introduce a
different case.
ואלא באונס משחרר ליה. Ve'ela be'ones mesharer leih.
Wait, did I skip a line? I must have skipped a line.
ואלא שמת הוא. Ve'ela shemes hu. Oh, thank you. ואלא שמת הוא,
Ve'ela shemes hu, hold on let me find my place again. אילימא
שמתה, eilima shemesah, thank you, מי איכא כתובה. mi ika kesuva. ואלא
שמת הוא, Ve'ela shemes hu, must be he died. And that's where
he's paying the כתובה. kesuva. אמאי מחזרת לו את השאר? amai machzeres
lo es hashar? Why give back the rest? נימא תנו לי בעלי
ואת מכחימו. nema tnuli ba'ali ve'at machimo. And we're now claiming that
everybody agrees she can make the claim תנו לי בעלי ואת מכחימו.
tnuli ba'ali ve'at machimo.
Okay, so if she can make that claim, then in the same
scenario where he's paying out the כתובה, kesuva, and by the way
you cannot split it into two cases, because it's very clear from
the structure of this בריתא braisa that they're the same case, because
it says pay the כתובה kesuva but deduct the rest. You know,
so we're clear the same case of her giving back is a
case that she's collecting the כתובה. kesuva. Do you- do you see
that? You cannot insert a different case here. So therefore the simplest
case would be he died. But we're now claiming that if he
died everybody says that she doesn't have to give anything back, תנו
לי בעלי ואת מכחימו. tnuli ba'ali ve'at machimo. So what's the case
that she's giving back and she's getting the כתובה? kesuva? If she
gets the כתובה kesuva she keeps the כסף קידושין kessef kiddushin and
she keeps the כיכר. kikar. Right, but the בריתא braisa has her
getting the כסף כתובה kessef kesuva but deducting the כסף קידושין. kessef
kiddushin. So what's that case? The simple case is he died, but
we're saying when he died she never gives it back. Okay, so
the Gemara says נימא תנו לי בעלי- nema tnuli ba'ali ואלא באשת
ישראל שזינתה. ve'ela be'eishes Yisrael she'zintzah. Maybe she committed adultery. Okay, ובמאי?
u-ve-mai? Now what's the case? אם ברצון, im be-ratzon, so if she
willfully committed adultery, so now the point being that he's forced to
divorce her, okay? And therefore he'd be forced to divorce her, give
her the כתובה, kesubah, and she would give back the ring, okay,
because it's obviously it's her fault. But the גמרא Gemara says wait
a minute, אם ברצון מי איכא כתובה? im be-ratzon mi ika kesubah?
Right, if she willfully committed adultery, she wouldn't get the כתובה. kesubah.
So that can't be the case. You have capital punishment, you have
well, there wouldn't be witnesses and warning or whatever, there's not enough
to give her capital punishment. But she could get it even before
even though there hasn't been the full marriage. Yes, yes, it is
a complete act of adultery even after the
קידושין. kiddushin. ואלא באונס. ve-ella be-ones. So fine, it's not adultery, it
is a case of rape. So in that case, מי שריא ליה?
mi sharya lei? So if he's married to ישראל, yisrael, you know,
God forbid she's raped, it doesn't make her forbidden to her husband.
ואלא באשת כהן. ve-ella be-eishet kohen. Okay, it's the wife of a
כהן kohen שנאנסה. she-ne'ensa. Okay, so now now we've got the scenario,
okay? Wife of a כהן, kohen, she was raped, God forbid, but
she was raped after קידושין. Kiddushin So now he's got to divorce
her, it's not her fault, okay? So he pays the כתובה. kesubah.
She though, now because she can't get married, she can't say תנו
לי בעלי ואשמח עמו, tenu li ba'ali ve-esmach imo, okay? It's not
his fault either, whatever. So now she's got to give back the
ring, okay? And or maybe she has to give back the ring,
but it's not a תנו לי בעלי tenu li ba'ali case. Okay,
so what's the debate? ובקידושין לטיבועין ניתנו קמיפלגי. u-ve-kiddushin le-tibu'in nitnu kamiflagi.
The question is whether the ring once it's given, it's done with.
רבי מאיר סבר קידושין לטיבועין ניתנו. rabbi meir savar kiddushin le-tibu'in nitnu.
רבי מאיר rabbi meir says she doesn't have to deduct anything. She
gets the full כתובה kesubah payment. End of story. The ring once
it's given is given. ורבי יהודה סבר לאו לטיבועין ניתנו. ve-rabbi yehuda
savar lav le-tibu'in nitnu. No, it's not true. מחזרת לו את השאר.
machzeret lo et ha-shear. In in this case. Yes, exactly.
Exactly. Or if she died, presumably it would be the same. You
have to give it back. Also not dependent on מנהג, minhag, it
seems. She just gives back the קידושין. Kiddushin ורבי יוסי ve-rabbi yossi
now רבי יוסי, rabbi yossi, what's this half that he's talking about?
מספקא ליה אי לטיבועין ניתנו אי לאו. mesafeka lei ei le-tibu'in nitnu
ei lav. He doesn't know which way to go and therefore he's
going to split the difference. והלכך קידשה בעשרים, ve-hilkach kidsha be-esrim, if
he gave her twenty, נותן לה שלושים חצאין. noten la sheloshim chatza'in.
So then the guy gives her thirty halves. What does that mean?
Let me just check the רשב"ם Rashbam here.
Right, so thirty half-שקלים shekalim are sixty זוז. zuz. So...
one minute... This is a כתובה? kesubah? This is a כתובה. kesubah.
One minute.
Okay, so the twenty and the thirty here are שקלים, shekalim, and
there's four זוז zuz to a שקל. shekel. Okay? So he gave
her twenty, which is basically eighty זוז, zuz, okay? And so now
she's got to give back of those eighty זוז zuz half, forty
זוז, zuz, okay? So where were we? רבי יוסי מספקא ליה אי
לטיבועין אי לאו הלכך קידשה בעשרים. rabbi yossi mesafeka lei ei le-tibu'in
ei lav hilkach kidsha be-esrim.
Okay,
so again twenty times four is eighty, eighty זוז. zuz. He
gave her that for כסף קידושין. kesef kiddushin. She has to give
back forty. So נותן לה שלושים חצאין. noten la sheloshim chatza'in. So
he has to give her thirty half thirty half-שקל shekel is sixty.
It's very confusing, okay? But you see how thirty half half-שקל shekel
is sixty. So she got here, she got twenty שקל. shekel. Let's
do it this way. She got twenty שקל, shekel, okay? So she's
going to have to give back twenty שקל, shekel, and therefore he's
going to give her thirty half-שקל. shekel. So thirty half-שקל shekel is
sixty, okay? Sixty זוז. zuz. He gave her twenty שקל, shekel, okay,
which was worth eighty זוז. zuz. So now what he's obligated to
give her
that's what he gave her for the כסף קידושין. kesef kiddushin. Now
he has to give her the balance. So the balance is thirty
half-שקל shekel which is sixty זוז. zuz. Why is that the balance?
Because he doesn't know whether this goes back or not. So we
treat it as half, that she got half of it. Okay, because
half, you know, you'd have to give it all back or none
back, you view it as half is given back. Okay, so what
he gave her now you give back half as it were. So
now what she's left with is conceptually forty זוז. zuz. So he
gives the balance which is now sixty זוז. zuz. Is that clear?
Okay, but that's assuming that it's a כתובת אלמנה. kesubas almanah. Right?
We're assuming that it was a hundred זוז כתובה, zuz kesubah, not
a two hundred זוז כתובה. zuz kesubah. Okay? All right, so that's
that case. Okay. But
let's just read the other one, one minute. נותן לה עשרים נותן
לה שלושים חצאין. קידשה בשלושים, kidsha bi-sheloshim, if he gave her thirty
שקלים, shekalim, okay, which was worth a hundred and twenty זוז. zuz.
So now she gives back half, you know conceptually, so she's left
with sixty. So now he's going to give her twenty half שקל,
Shekel, which would be forty, and that'll be the balance. So, so,
קיצץ בשלושים נותן לו
עשרים חצאי. Kitzetz b'shloshim nosen lo esrim chatzei. Yes, Rabbi Dov.
I'm sorry, I still missed the distinction between the שושבינות and the
סבלונות. Sablonot.
The שושבינות are the gifts that are given by friends at the
חופה Chuppah and then when the friends get married it's reciprocated. סבלונות
Sablonot are given by the groom to the bride between the קידושין
Kiddushin and the נישואין, Nissu'in, after the... Isn't this very clear? The
picture's just
self-explanatory.
The גמרא Gemara is not very clear,
but I think you deduced it correctly. It's a כהן's Kohen wife,
it's רייד. reid. They were already married. Does she get the כתובה?
Ketubah? Yes, she does. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this,
אמר רב יוסף בר מניומי אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Yosef bar
Minyumi amar Rav Nachman, בכל מקום שנהגו להחזיר מחזירין. bechol makom she'nahagu
l'hachzir machzirin. Okay,
so every place that they have the מנהג Minhag to give it
back, you give it back. What does that mean? When the woman
dies. Okay, so meaning it sounds like he's saying that basically that
it's not קידושין לטיבועין ניתנו. Kiddushin l'tibu'in nitnu. It always goes, it
always goes by the מנהג. Minhag.
ותרגומא בנהרדעא שאר בבל. V'targuma b'Nahardea shear Bavel. What does it mean?
Hold on.
שאר. shear.
What does it mean? ותרגומא בנהרדעא שאר. V'targuma b'Nahardea shear. Hold on.
I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I put the punctuation in the wrong place.
ותרגומא, V'targuma, the explanation of all the places where they have this
practice you give it back, excuse me, is נהרדעא. Nahardea. Okay, in
נהרדעא, Nahardea, those are places where the practice was to give it
back and therefore you would always give it back and we would
not say that it's קידושין לטיבועין ניתנו. Kiddushin l'tibu'in nitnu. So now
that we said that's true about נהרדעא, Nahardea, the גמרא Gemara says
שאר בבל מאי? Shear Bavel mai? What's it say about the rest
of בבל? Bavel? So רבה ורב יוסף דאמרי תרוייהו, Rabbah v'Rav Yosef
d'amri tarvaihu, they both say
מאורי הדרי קידושי לא הדרי. Ma'ori hadri Kiddushei lo hadri. So מאורי
Ma'ori goes back, okay. Now we describe מוהר Mohar as the סבלונות,
Sablonot, which is very interesting because the biblical מוהר Mohar is כסף
קידושין. Kesef Kiddushin. Right, but what's fascinating here is how the word
evolves to mean something else. Now actually the כתובה Ketubah of the
two hundred זוז, Zuz, right? Remember here we said the שקל Shekel
is four זוז. Zuz. So the כתובה's Ketubah two hundred זוז Zuz
is how many שקל? Shekel? Let's see, I have math geniuses in
the room. Fifty, right? That's the חמישים כסף chamishim kesef in the
תורה. Torah. So the כתובה Ketubah is really a rabbinic reframing of
the מוהר. Mohar. But here the word מוהר Mohar sort of moves,
you know, from the קידושין Kiddushin to the כתובה, Ketubah, but here
we see the word makes a pit stop, or at least the
use of the word, right, in this gifts that are being given
here. Okay, so the מוהר Mohar is these gifts here that are
given. So he says, so let's read it, רבה ורב יוסף דאמרי
תרוייהו מאורי הדרי. Rabbah v'Rav Yosef d'amri tarvaihu Ma'ori hadri. In the
rest of בבל, Bavel, the מאורי Ma'ori would be given back, the
סבלונות Sablonot would be given back, okay, if she died or he
died presumably. Okay, קידושי לא הדרי, Kiddushei lo hadri, but the קידושין
Kiddushin doesn't go back. Okay, that's either לטיבועין ניתנו l'tibu'in nitnu or
however you explain it. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, רב פפא
Rav Pappa said, הלכתא, hilchata, the הלכה halacha is, בין שמת הוא
בין שמתה היא, bein shemet hu bein shemetah hi, whether he dies
or she dies, והדרי בהו v'hadri behu or whether he is the
one that basically says I'm calling this off, I guess, and giving
a גט, Get, מאורי הדרי, Ma'ori hadri, the סבלונות Sablonot goes back,
קידושי לא הדרי. Kiddushei lo hadri. Okay, the קידושין Kiddushin. doesn't go
back. קידושין Kiddushin is לטיבועין ניתנו. l'tibu'in nitnu. So even if basically
she's the one that dies, she doesn't have to give back the
קידושין. Kiddushin Now let's
say it's not just she died, let's say she actually is the
one, meaning you know, but she actually is the one calling it
off, okay. Then maybe she would have to, then let's talk about
that. Under all cases where it's not like she's the initiator, okay,
as long as she's not the initiator, okay, it basically says that
she gets to keep it all. Okay, so, excuse me,
בין שמתה היא והדרי בהו, bein shemetah hi v'hadri behu, the מאורי,
Ma'ori, this always goes back, these gifts always goes back because these
gifts are seen to be sort of a build up to the
נישואין. Nissu'in. So since the נישואין Nissu'in never took place, these gifts
always go back. The כסף קידושין Kesef Kiddushin never goes back. But
that's when she wasn't the initiator. So no matter who's to blame
or who died or whatever, as long as she's not the initiator,
these gifts are all for the חופה Chuppah and they go back.
back, the ring doesn't. But let's say she's the initiator, in that
case would the ring go back? So, so the גמרא says, where
were we? הדרא בי אייהי, Hadra be ihi, if she's the initiator.
Now again, it could be that the husband says, I don't care
that you don't want to go through with נישואין, Nissu'in, like, you
know, you can't force me to give a גט. get. But presumably
we also wouldn't force her to move in with him, right? So
she's like refusing to go through with נישואין. Nissu'in.
So because she's refusing to go through with נישואין, Nissu'in, he has
no choice but to give, I mean he could stay, whatever, you
know, maybe the בית דין Beis Din would compel him if he's
refusing to go through. But anyway, it doesn't matter. The dynamics are
such that it's because of she's the one that's insisting and initiating.
Okay, so הדרא בי אייהי, Hadra be ihi, אפילו קידושין נמי הדרי,
afillu Kiddushin nami hadre, if she's the initiator then she's got to
give back the ring. אמימר אמר, Amemar amar, קידושי לא הדרי. Kiddushei
lo hadre. No,
even in that case she would not give back the ring. And
know why? We've got a very important sort of, you know, reason
in terms of halachic boundary issues. גזירה שמא יאמרו קידושין תופסין באחותה.
Gzeira shema yomru Kiddushin tofin ba'achotah. Because what's going to happen? She's
going to say, I'm not going through with נישואין, Nissu'in, take your
ring back. So of course it has to be a גט. get.
But people are going to see that she gave the ring back.
So a normal person might read that as the whole thing got
called off and it never took place. Right? You might visually see
that as a reversal and as an undoing. And therefore say she's
not a גרושה. Grusha. Okay, so א', A, maybe she'll marry a
כהן. Kohen. But ב', B, or he'll now go ahead and turn
around and say, fine, you don't want to go through with it,
I'll marry your sister. Now he's not, he can't marry the sister
after he's been married to her, right? But because the ring is
going back, it'll look like maybe the קידושין Kiddushin never took place.
So it says, we cannot allow the ring to ever go back
besides any דיני ממונות dinei mammonos issues, it's going to be way
too confusing in terms of getting thinking that maybe the קידושין Kiddushin
didn't take place. Yes. Can he marry the sister after קידושין if
there were no נישואין? Nissu'in? No. No. That's correct. Okay, so unless
she dies.
When the רשב"ם Rashbam talks about the מוהר, mohar, he says it's
the
מוהר mohar הוא ממון שמקדים לה אתה בימי אירוסין שהיא כותב בכתובתה.
hu mammon shemakdim lah atta bimei eirusin shehi koteiv bechusubasah. So is
it like the תוספת, tosefet, like a
תוספת? tosefet? You write that מוהר mohar amount in the כתובה, Kesubah,
so is it like the
תוספתא Tosefta
of?
Yeah, it's possible it might be that. Yeah, I mean he is
saying that there are two stages of the מוהר, mohar, but yeah,
I don't think it's, it's not the תוספת. tosefet. He somehow saying
it's recorded in the כתובה. Kesubah. That's not the תוספת, tosefet, the
תוספת tosefet is an amount that's paid, I'll have to unpack that,
okay? But okay, but it's good that you note that. That he
says מוהר mohar is like a different, a different weight. Because he's
sensitive to the fact that the מוהר mohar means is a word
that comes to be the basis for the כתובה. Kesubah. So he
wants to read מוהר mohar as a type of a סבלונות Savlonos
that's connected to the כתובה. Kesubah. Yeah, but I'll have to sort
of fully figure out exactly what he's getting at. Okay. Yeah? If
the נישואין Nissu'in never took place, so the marriage was never consummated,
right? What? If the, no,
that, well, the marriage wasn't consummated. The קידושין was effective, it still
requires a גט. get. If by consummated you mean that they didn't
actually have intercourse, that is correct. But if you mean that the
marriage wasn't effective, I mean, the marriage wasn't, but the betrothal was,
legally she's married. It's confusing for us because we think about engagement
and marriage. Betrothal is legally married, okay? So the נישואין Nissu'in means
that they're living together. Alright, so רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar,
now רב אשי Rav Ashi says, no, I'm not concerned about that.
גיטא מוכח עלה. Gita mochiach alah. She has a, she needs a
גט, get, so just because people see the ring go back, nobody's
going to think she's not a divorcee, they see the
גט. get. והדר רב אשי בדבוריה, Vehadar Rav Ashi bediburei, but what
רב אשי Rav Ashi is saying is foolish, דאיכא דשמע בהא ולא
שמע בהא. de'ika desham'a beha velo sham'a beha. You know what? You
know, what is it, never underestimate the intelligence of the American public
or whatever?
No, people don't always, like, know everything. Just because there's a גט,
get, they all heard that she gave the ring back, they didn't
hear about the גט. get. So this is a very reasonable safeguard.
Okay, fine. Now we're moving on. שושבינות נגבית בבית דין. Shoshvinos nigbis
beveiv din. So that was about this whole question about whether the
ring goes back and the סבלונות Savlonos goes back and all of
that, okay? Okay, and all of that was a digression about תנו
לי בעלי ואשמח בו tinu li ba'ali ve'esmach bo that if this
guy, that if the, you know, that if the guy dies, the
שושבינות would not have to repay a, give a gift if the
groom actually dies. Okay. שושבינות נגבית בבית דין, Shoshvinos nigbis beveiv din,
שושבינות is collected in בית דין. Beis Din. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan.
חמשה דברים נאמרו בשושבינות, Chamishah devarim neemru beshoshvinos, five things. נגבית בבית
דין, Nigbis beveiv din,
once you received it, it's a real debt and they can collect
in בית דין Beis Din paying back. וחוזרת בעונתה, Vechozeres be'onasah,
it has to be given back in its specific time, right? If
you look at the רשב"ם, last line, כשישא האיש יחזיר לו שושבינותו
ולא קודם, kesheyissa ha'ish yachazir lo shoshvinuso velo kodem, you can't like
pre-pay it, right? Okay. וחוזרת בעונתה, Vechozeres be'onasah, ואין בה משום ריבית,
ve'ein bah mishum ribbis,
let's say you want to give a bigger gift back than the
one you received, right? You can so you imagine that, you know,
your friend is not as well off as you are, you know,
you receive a nice modest gift, you want to return one that's
more appropriate for, you know, your income. It's not a... so it's
ironic. It's נגבית בבית דין nigves b'veit din so it's a real
debt that you can now get the בית דין veit din to
come and collect, but the amount is somehow not specified. What if...
what if it's the reverse, right? What if you gave back a
more modest gift? Presumably that's okay too, right? So your wealthy friend
gave you a big gift, you're going to give back a modest
one, presumably that's okay. So it's a very strange type of a
debt. It's a debt with this collectible in בית דין beit din
but without a particular dollar amount. I mean I don't know if
there would be like a minimum, right? You can't give back like
a penny or something, I don't know. Okay, I had a cousin
who was once in Israel with basically he was at this ישיבה
yeshiva and in the ישיבה yeshiva like every time somebody got an
עליה aliyah they would say יתן מתנה לבית הכנסת yitein matana l'veit
haknesset מתנה לבית הכנסת. matana l'veit haknesset. So finally they put up
a like a little like a sign that said אין מתנה פחותה
מחמישה שקלים. ein matana p'chusa me-chamisha shekalim. Okay, so the guy gets
an עליה aliyah and he says חצי מתנה. chatzi matana. So
anyway so I don't know maybe there is some minimum but it
is ironic, right? There is no ריבית, ribis, it's a debt. So
but I'm guessing you could give back less than you received, let's
say you don't have the you know you're not as wealthy, the
means. ואינה שביעית משמטתה. ve-eina shevi'is m'shamatata. So again what?
חצי עליה. chatzi aliyah. Right. Okay, שביעית shevi'is does not annul it.
Now why not? Okay, I mean if it's collected in בית
דין. beit din. So
שמיטה shmita if the שמיטה shmita year passes you still have to
give it back. So it's like this weird thing that it's a
debt but it's a but there's a social dimension so it's not
something that's about the dynamics of a borrower and a lender like
לא יגוש את רעהו ואת אחיו. lo yigos es re'eihu v'es achiv.
To be נוגש nogeis means like to you know to exact as
a creditor exacts from a debtor, right? So here even though I
could go to בית דין beit din fundamentally the dynamic is one
of friends and of equals and not of the power dynamic of
a borrower and a lender. If you look at תוספות Tosfos like
תוספות Tosfos says דלא קרי ביה לא יגוש. d'lo kari bei lo
yigos. Okay, so it's again it is a debt, it's a חוב
chov but it's not a חוב chov of that sort of power
dynamic of a lender and a borrower.
Okay, I mean the גמרא is actually going to say that. תוספות
Tosfos just pointing out the גמרא ahead of time. Okay, ואין
הבכור נוטל בה פי שנים ve-ein habechor notel bah pi shenayim and
if a when it's going to go back to the middle in
this case, right, well we erased it but the case where it
would go back to the whole family the בכור bechor doesn't get
a double portion. Any guesses why the בכור bechor doesn't get a
double portion? You should be able to figure that out by now.
Why would the בכור bechor when it gets reciprocated and goes back
to the family the whole family
it was what? It wasn't in possession. It was ראוי and not
מוחזק. Exactly. So okay so now the גמרא is going to go
through this. Okay. נגבית בבית דין מאי טעמא? nigves b'veit din mai
ta'ama? Why? כמלוה דמיא k'milveh damya because it's like a loan.
דמיא, damya, it's like a loan. Okay, now it skips over the
חוזרת בעונתה chozeres b'onata although the רשב"ם says that some גרסאות girsa'os
had that as well. נגבית בבית דין ואינה חוזרת בעונתה nigves b'veit
din v'eina chozeres b'onata because it's like a loan and a loan
where the payment date is when the next person gets married. Okay,
ואין בה משום רבית. ve-ein bah mishum ribis. There's no ריבית ribis
דלאו אדעתא דהכי יהב ליה. d'lav ada'ata d'hachi yahav lei. It wasn't
with that sort of thing in mind, meaning it was understood that
you can pay back with a different amount. It wasn't a loan
that you pay back the same amount, you can pay back with
a different amount.
Okay, יהב ליה. yahav lei. So you're not obligated to give back
X back actually you know presumably the norm would be to give
back the same.
ואינה שביעית משמטתה דלא קרינא ביה לא יגוש. ve-eina shevi'is m'shamatata d'lo
karina bei lo yigos. Okay and if you look at the רשב"ם
this לא יגוש lo yigos the power dynamic I was talking about
שאינו יכול לדחקו בביתין בשביעית שהרי לא הגיע זמנו. she-eino yachol l'dachko
b'veitin b'shvi'is she-harei lo higia zmano. Now I gave a whole power
dynamic thing, the רשב"ם explains it as a more technical point that
if your friend did not get remarried yet then it is not
yet the time to be paid up, right? So I got married,
you gave me the gift. שמיטה shmita comes and you haven't gotten
married yet. So if it's a loan the time for payment hasn't
come about yet when שמיטה shmita hits, שמיטה shmita doesn't annul it.
All right, so I like my explanation better because I like thinking
about the whole power dynamic of a loan. Okay, but for the
way the רשב"ם is explaining it it's more technical. The נפקא מינה
nafka mina would be let's say I got married I got it
you know you got
married I went to your wedding and I haven't had a chance
yet to pay it and then שמיטה shmita came. Right? So according
to the way the רשב"ם reads it שמיטה shmita would annul it
because my obligation has already come about. Okay, ואין הבכור נוטל בראוי
כבמוחזק ve-ein habechor notel b'ra'uy k'v'muchzak ואין הבכור נוטל בראוי כבמוחזק. ve-ein
habechor notel b'ra'uy k'v'muchzak. I'm sorry I skipped one. ואין הבכור נוטל
בפי שנים דהוה ליה ראוי ve-ein habechor notel b'pi shenayim d'hava lei
ra'uy ואין הבכור. ve-ein habechor. ואין הבכור נוטל בראוי כבמוחזק Ve'ein habechor
notel barauy k'b'muchzak ואין הבכור נוטל בראוי כבמוחזק, ve'ein habechor notel barauy
k'b'muchzak, I'm sorry, I said it twice, ואין הבכור נוטל בשניים דהוי
ליה ראוי ve'ein habechor notel bishnayim d'havelei rauy ואין הבכור נוטל בראוי
כבמוחזק. ve'ein habechor notel barauy k'b'muchzak. He does not get what's stuff
coming back the same way he gets with stuff that's already in
the possession. Okay, I think we will end there.